Hello, welcome back to our course. Today, we are going to talk about factors
and data frames. What is a factor variable? So a factor variable is a
variable or a vector of class 'factor'. And what are the advantages of having factors?
Well, they are useful for a correct implementation in statistical modeling.
and analyses. They are very useful in many different types of graphics,
and they are more efficient when it comes to the memory usage
compared to characters. But as you'll see, factors
in R are stored as vectors of integer values.
So here we have this example, we have a vector F, with two different values, 1 and 2.
And then, if we check the class of F, the class of F is numeric.
But, if we'd like to coerce that vector to a factor,
we could write as.factor, and now we can see that the class
has changed to factor, but the values stayed the same. But now we have an additional information, that
we have two different levels, 1 and 2. Another way to create factors is to apply this factor function to our vector F
and then to define two labels, M and F. Now, once we look at the output, we can see that f.labels
has as its values M and F. And here, the levels are M and F, so indeed you can see that 1 and 2 were
transformed to M and F. But actually, if now we check
the structure of this object in R, you can see that the structure is as follows: We have
this integer vector, with an additional information that it has two levels.
So indeed, R stores factors as a vector of integers with
labels, and labels are of our choice. An alternative way to create a factor is to apply this factor function to a vector with different
characters. So, for example, here we have "smoker" and "non-smoker", and then you can see, as an output, we have
smoker and no smoker, and then we have that additional information of different levels.
Let us now pass to data frames. So, as you might remember from our previous videos,
matrices can only contain one data type. And, oftentimes in machine learning, statistics or AI,
analysis are often required for data of different types. And, data frame can contain several data types:
Numeric integers, factors, and usually, in each row of a data frame, we have a different observation.
And in each column, you have a different variable. For example, we can think about having different observations being different cities:
Paris, Berlin, Rome, etc. And columns could correspond to different characteristics
of these cities. For example the number of inhabitants, latitude, longitude, etc.
And then to create a data frame, we need to have vectors
of the same length. So now, here we have an example, we have three
factors. The first one is A, with numeric values B, with this factor vector, and then we have another vector
with numeric values. And now, how can we create a data frame? We could apply a function data.frame
to these three vectors bundled together, and then we could also
give names to different columns of our data frame. So here you can see that I gave them names age, sex, and siblings, and here,
once we now look at the output, we can see that we have a
data frame with different rows, and with different columns
which correspond to age, sex, and siblings. Another way to construct a data frame is to
do it directly from a matrix, so here you can see that I constructed that matrix A.
The class of A is a matrix, an array, but if I now try to coerce that to a data frame, I could use a function as.data.frame.
And indeed, now you can see that the elements inside are the same. We have different labels for columns
V1 to V4, and our rows
are just indexed: 1, 2, and 3, and then we can see that the class of A.df is now a data frame.
How can we access the elements of our data frame? Well, we could do it through bracketing,
or we could do it through using this dollar sign. For example, if I would like to access the first column,
I could just apply this bracket to my data frame, and then put 1 on the second place.
Another way is to use a dollar sign, and you might remember that
in lists, it was similar. So, here I take mydf$Age,
and then I can see all the observations for the age column.
Another way is to put the name of a column inside the bracket on the second place.
We could also access a particular element of our data frame. For example, here I would like to access an element
in the third row and third column, and this element is 0 here.
We could also change a particular element. How can we do it? Well, we access that particular element and assign it
a value of our choice. Here, it would be 2. And now, if I once again check how this element looks like, you can see that, instead of having 0, we have now 2.
If we would like to access not only one element or
one column, but a few columns, how can we do it?
For example, we could create a vector with two different names. Here, I would like to access columns age and sex
and put it on the second place of our bracket. And here, also, I'm showing you how I can
show you all the rows
apart from the second one. So, for example, here you can see that I don't want to have
the second row in my data frame, so basically I just use minus 2.
Another way to access different columns, different variables,
is through attaching the entire data frame. So, if I use function attach, and the name of my data frame, then you can see that I can access these different variables directly. I just type Age
and then you can see that as an output. I can just type sex, and we have
a factor vector with different levels. And similarly for siblings.
If I now would like to, not be able to
access these elements directly, then I can detach my data frame from my session.
And indeed, if I detach it, then I cannot anymore access
particular elements from that data frame. Here you can see that we
have an error. Okay. We could also access elements through creating these
logical operations. For example, imagine that I would like to access
elements, which correspond to males and males who are
more than 30 years old. So here you can see that
on the first place of our bracket, I inserted this logical expressions,
and then you can see that, indeed, I now can see only the fifth row,
which correspond to a person who is 76 years old, so indeed, the condition is checked,
and then to a male, because sex is M. If I would like to, for example, access males and
people over 30, but not necessarily males, so basically male or over 30,
how can I do it? I put these two conditions, but instead of AND operator,
I insert OR. How can we see that this indeed worked? Well, in the output, now I can see that I have.
males, M, M, M, M of different ages,
and I have females, but only who are more than 30 years old, because we have females,
And then this is 43, 41, and 46.
We could also see how can I add a particular variable to my data frame:
In my data frame, we had 3 variables, age, sex, and siblings.
But now, imagine that I would like to add an income variable to my data frame.
How do I do it? Well, through a dollar sign. So, I do mydf$,
I give a name to my variable, to my column. And then I assign to it that vector with different values, and you can see now that I
have an enlarged data frame with 3 columns, and then the fourth one is the one I have just added.
We could also rename and delete certain variables, certain columns, so here you can see that if I apply function names to my data frame,
then I have 4 different columns. I have age, sex, siblings, and income, and imagine that now I would like to change the name Income
to IncomeUSD. So how do I do it? I apply this function names
to my data frame, and then in the bracket, I select that particular name, so names, once again, of my data frame.
Was before Income, but now I would like to assign to it a name, IncomeUSD.
So here you can see that I'm doing it through that arrow.
And another way is to select a particular
value from these names, because you can see that names have
four elements, so I could just access the fourth element, and I could assign the new name IncomeUSD.
I could also remove certain variables. How can I do it? Well, I could just access
that particular variable, that particular column through a dollar sign, and I could assign to it
NULL. Then you can see if we see the output of my data frame, we have now 3 columns: Sex,
Siblings, we removed age, we cannot see age anymore, and then instead of Income, we have IncomeUSD.
Another handy thing we could do with our data frames is to
sort them. How do I do it? Well, I apply function order to
my bracket on the first place. So here you can see that I would like to sort
by column Sex. So, to my data frame, I apply this function order by sex,
and what is the result? Indeed, I can see that my entire data frame
is sorted by values of the column sex. So we have F, F,
F, and then M, M, M. We can also sort by several variables.
So here, first, I would like to order by sex,
and then, for each sex, I would like to have them ordered by the number of siblings.
So here, we can see that I do it through inserting order with two different
conditions. And indeed, as an output, I can see that I have a
data frame ordered by sex, because first I have F, then I have M.
And then I have, within each category of sex, I have
different number of siblings. So, you can see that I have 1, 1, 1, 3
For females, and then also males are sorted by the number of siblings.